Guide to the International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers, Local 25 Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, Local 25 records
1933-1971
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections
1608
1608-001
International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers. Local 25 (Tacoma, Wash.)
3.61 cubic feet 4 boxes and one oversize vertical folder
Records of a Tacoma, Washington union of Mine, Mill and Smelter workers relating to grievances and negotiations, arbitration of several grievances, agreements
The International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers (formerly the Western Federation of Miners) was formed in 1916, and weathered repeated accusations of Communism against its leadership during the 1940s and 1950s; in 1967 it merged with the United Steelworkers of America. Local 25 of the International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers was organized in 1933 by workers at the Tacoma Smelter of the American Smelting and Refining Company. It continued as Local 25 of the United Steelworkers of America when the International merged with the United Steelworkers. The Tacoma Smelter, located on Commencement Bay in the company town of Ruston, Washington, had been in existence since1889. It was founded by William R. Rust as the Tacoma Smelting and Refining Company, and began operating in 1890. In 1905 the smelter was purchased by the American Smelting and Refining Company. The facility was originally used to smelt and refine lead, but in 1912 it was converted to a copper smelter and refinery.
The materials are arranged in five subgroups:
Administrative Records of Local 25, 1933-1971
International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, Local 25, Ladies' Auxiliary, 1949-1952, undated
International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, Local 25, Workmen's Safety Committee of the Tacoma Smelter, 1944-1968
Workmen's Hospital and Benefit Committee of the Tacoma Smelter
International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, 1948-1965
The papers consist primarily of Local 25's administrative records, including materials relating to grievances and negotiations, arbitration of several grievances, agreements with the Tacoma Smelter, and Local 25's newsletter The Straight of It. There is minimal documentation of a strike in 1946 and a lockout in 1950, and a more significant amount of material relating to a lockout and extended work stoppage in 1959. Most material dates from before the merger of the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers with the United Steelworkers of America, but some ephemera from after the merger are present in Administrative Records.
The Ladies' Auxiliary material consists primarily of minutes and a ritual book. The Workmen's Safety Committee material includes minutes, correspondence, accident reports and newsletters. The Hospital and Benefit Committee material includes correspondence, minutes and summaries of health and welfare plans. The material from the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers consists primarily of board meeting minutes, reports, fact sheets, newsletters and bulletins, and subject files concerning bargaining with the American Smelting and Refining Company, and a union representation campaign in Idaho.
Major correspondents include John Caughlan, Local 25's attorney and several executive officers of the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, Local 25, 19 early 1960's: William E. Lee, Business Agent/Financial Secretary; Elmer Olson, Secretary/Secretary-Treasurer/Financial Secretary; Irving Dichter, Secretary-Treasurer; Arthur W. Stuart, Research Director; John Clarke, President; and Al Skinner, President.
The papers are also available on microfilm.
Records are stored off site; advance notice required for use.
Access restricted: For terms of access, contact repository.
Gift of the United Steelworkers Union, Local 25, via Rodger Vandegrift in 1971.
Eight state and federal government publications were offered to the Government Publications Collection in the Libraries.
The records of the International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers Union are presently in the Archives, University of Colorado at Boulder Libraries.
Caughlan, John,$d1909-1999; Clark, John; Dichter, Irving; Lee, William E.; Olsen, Elmer W.; Skinner, A. C.,$q(Al C.); International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers.$bLocal 25 (Tacoma, Wash.)$vArchives; United Steelworkers of America.$bLocal 25 (Tacoma, Wash.); Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Tacoma (Wash.)$xEconomic conditions; Metal-workers$xLabor unions$zWashington (State)$zTacoma$vArchives; Collective bargaining$xMetal-workers$zWashington (State)$zTacoma; Labor movement$zWashington (State)$zTacoma; Metal-workers$xEmployees$xLabor unions$zWashington (State)$zTacoma; Mineral industries$xEmployees$xLabor unions$zWashington (State)$zTacoma; Strikes and lockouts$zWashington (State)$zTacoma; Newsletters; Administrative records; Agreements
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Washington (State); Mines and Mineral Resources
- Administrative Records, 1933-1971, undated
  Some documentation from the International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers is also present.
  - Organizational Features, 1941, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - General Correspondence, 1941-1969, undated (Box-folder 1/2-5)
  - Interorganizational Correspondence, 1954-1967 (Box-folder 1/6-17)
    Correspondence between Local 25 and the International Union, including its American Smelting and Refining Company Council
  - Minutes, 1951, undated (Box-folder 1/18)
    Primarily contains minutes of shop stewards' meetings but also union committee meetings, a meeting of the Seattle-Tacoma "LE Committee" (apparently concerned with environmental and safety issues, but the actual name is unknown), publicity committee meetings and some which are completely unidentified.
  - Agreements, 1945-1968 (Box-folder 1/19-24)
    Folder 1/24 contains an undated summary of agreements from 1937-1954
  - Agreements - Other Unions and Locals, 1948, 1950, 1953, 1955 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Wage Scales, 1941, 1954, undated (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Manual of Smelter Workers' Duties, undated (Box-folder 1/27)
    Manual includes wage scales; folder also contains one page of operating instructions for selenium scrubbing equipment.
  - Grievances and Negotiations, 1948-1963, undated (Box-folder 1/28-33)
  - Arbitration, 1943-1944, 1948, 1958, 1960 (Box-folder 1/34-38)
  - Hearings; Hearings on Unemployment Compensation 1959 (Box-folder 1/39)
  - Appeals; Appeals - Washington State Department of Employment Security, 1960 (Box-folder 1/40)
  - Subject Files
    - 1946 Strike, 1946, undated (Box-folder 2/1)
    - 1950 Lockout, 1950, undated (Box-folder 2/2)
    - 1959 Health and Welfare Contracts, 1959, 1960 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - 1959 Lockout, 1955, 1959, undated (Box-folder 2/4-7)
      Includes correspondence, negotiations, clippings and other related materials.
    - 1959 Negotiations (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Building and Playground, 1950-1955 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Coeur d'Alene Strike, 1960 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Japanese Competition for Copper Smelting, 1961, 1962 (Box-folder 2/11)
      Includes one letter from Representative Thor Tollefson to William Lee, then Local 25's business agent.
    - Lead Quotas, 1963, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Pension Plan, 1941, 1956-1968 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - Slavonian Hall Building, 1958 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - United Steelworkers of America, 1968, undated (Box-folder 2/15-21)
      Includes two letters from members withdrawing from the union, and flyers regarding union issues, both local and national. Also present are materials produced by the United Steelworkers of America, including copies of its constitution, adopted resolutions, reports and ephemera.
    - William Lee Executive Board Campaign (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Membership Records, 1931-1970 (Box-folder 2/23-3/2)
    Includes yearly member lists, meeting attendance records, withdrawals claimed, reclassification requests and other materials.
  - Election Materials, 1941-1959, undated (Box-folder 3/3-7)
    Includes ballots, tallies, resolution drafts, campaign ephemera and other materials.
  - Financial Records, 1955-1967, undated (Box-folder 3/8-14)
    Includes monthly and quarterly reports to the international union.
  - Newsletter; The Straight Of It, 1945-1964, 1971, undated (Box-folder 3/15-17)
  - Newsletters; Other Organizations, 1964 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Press Releases, 1963 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Lists; Tacoma Smelter Staff, undated (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Ephemera of Local 25 and others, 1947, 1961, undated (Box-folder 3/21-23)
  - Legislation, 1962, 1965, 1969 (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Clippings, 1961, 1965, 1969, undated (Box-folder 3/25-26)
    One folder contains the contents of an envelope labeled "News Clippings News Tribune (Copper Situation) 1961"
- International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, Local 25, Ladies' Auxiliary, 1949-1952, undated
  - Ritual Book, undated (Box-folder 3/27)
  - Minutes, 1949-1952, undated (Box-folder 3/28-29)
- International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, Local 25, Workmen's Safety Committee of the Tacoma Smelter, 1944-1968, undated
  - General Correspondence, 1956-1968 (Box-folder 3/30)
  - Minutes, 1957-1968 (Box-folder 3/31-39)
  - Minutes; Washington State Metal Workers' Safety Committee, 1961, 1966-1967, 1970 (Box-folder 3/40)
  - Subject File; Safety Tours, 1956 (Box-folder 3/41)
  - Accident Reports, 1952, 1956-1968 (Box-folder 3/42-43)
  - Accident Reports; Other American Smelting and Refining Company Plants, 1962, 1964 (Box-folder 3/44)
  - Newsletters, 1957 (Box-folder 3/45)
  - Newsletters; Other Organizations, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 3/46)
  - Reports; Other Organizations, 1960, 1962 (Box-folder 3/47-48)
  - Safety and Health Standards, 1956, 1958, 1960, 1970, undated (Box-folder 3/49-50)
  - Safety Rules and Regulations; American Smelting and Refining Company, 1944, 1949-1950, 1959
  - Conference and Convention Files; Governor's Eleventh Annual Industrial Safety Committee, 1960 (Box-folder 3/51)
  - Ephemera, 1961, undated (Box-folder 3/52)
  - Press Releases, 1959, 1962 (Box-folder 3/53)
- Workmen's Hospital and Benefit Committee of the Tacoma Smelter, 1941-1967, undated
  - Organizational Features, undated (Box-folder 4/1)
  - General Correspondence, 1957-1967 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Minutes, 1955, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Agreements, 1952, 1956, 1962, undated (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Resolutions, 1952 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Appeals, 1962 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Health and Welfare Plan Summaries, 1941-1964, undated (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Ephemera, 1953, undated (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Clippings, undated (Box-folder 4/9)
- International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers, 1948-1965, undated
  - Minutes, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 4/10)
    Minutes of the Executive Board and Canvassing Committee.
  - Statements, 1961, 1963 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Arbitration, 1961 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Fact Sheets, 1950, 1961-1963, undated (Box-folder 4/13)
    Includes material from the Education and Research Departments.
  - Reports of the Canvassing Committee and Research Department, 1963, undated (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Newsletter; Mine-Mill Legislative Letter, 1948-1965 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Bulletins
    - Mine Mill Research Department, 1950
    - Mine Mill Strike Bulletin, 1959 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Mine-Mill's Bargaining Bulletin, 1964 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Officers & Stewards Bulletin, 1964 (Box-folder 4/17)
    - Mine Mill Staff Bulletin, 1965 (Box-folder 4/17)
  - Conference and Convention Files, 1959, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 4/18-19)
    Includes material from annual national conventions.
  - Subject Files
    - 1959 Demands (Box-folder 4/20)
    - 1964 Bargaining, 1964, undated (Box-folder 4/21-22)
    - Bunker Hill Mine Union Representation Vote, 1964, undated (Box-folder 4/23)
      Ephemera produced by the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers as well as the United Steelworkers of America and Northwest Metal Workers, who were competing to represent workers at Idaho's Bunker Hill mine.
  - Press Releases, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 4/24)
  - Health and Welfare Manual, undated (Box-folder 4/25)
  - Ephemera, 1964, undated (Box-folder 4/26)
  - Ephemera, 1964, undated (Box-folder:oversize Oversize V.F. 84)